Okay, our next speaker is going to be
talking to us about new tools for
assessing the therapeutic activity and
efficacy for Angelmen syndrome. And I
believe that we actually have Lena Han
who's going to be presenting on behalf
of Albert Young, who I assume is not
here. Otherwise, you wouldn't be
standing up and walking here. Or you've
grown a lot of hair and you've shrunk a
little bit and you look like a different
person. Come on up.
Because that's not Albert that I'm sure
of.
Hello everyone. Uh today I'd like to be
here to share some results from uh four
projects from our group and our
collaborators on new tools for assessing
therapeutic activity and efficacy.
So
uh first uh our group generated a human
and syndrome class 2 reporter cell line
by integrating a green floren center
protein gene into the genome and this uh
reporter cell line can be used for
therapeutic screening. Uh so when the uh
paternal UV3 is anti uh is uh inactive
the cell is dark but after we add the
drug if the drug is effective uh when
the drug restore the expression of
paternal UV3A then the cells turning
green uh light up green. So the reporter
signal can be uh observed on the
microscope or be analyzed by
flowcytometry directly. No antibbody
needed. Uh this work just published
recently.
Uh second,
a desirable tool to detect UV3 bio
activity is highly uh desirable for both
potency and biomarker essay uh in
therapeutics evaluation and disease
monitoring. Our group developed this uh
rapid and highly sensitive essay that
can be detect functional UV3 B activity
with one or more sensitivity and it can
discriminate while type U3 with mutant.
Uh
we also successfully applied this essay
for uh multiple different biological
samples including uh human stem cell
lysate uh cell culture supernent and
recombinant cell penetrating peptide
UV3A.
Uh this work uh published earlier this
year.
We also developed a scalable uh oops
we also developed a scalable
electrophysiology
platform by using macro electro
electrode aris. uh each basket shaped
MEA can hold one organoid and it
contains 12 independent
uh macro electrodes that can
confformally interface with the
organoid. This platform can be used for
high throughput brain activity recording
and drug screening. The right side
figure uh is a plot uh recordings the
voltage recordings of 74 organoids human
organoids uh in parallel which is the
largest data set uh reported to date for
the organoid electro psychology.
At last we also um analyzed the role of
UB3A
in human cerebral organoids by using
single cell RNA sequencing with H9 wild
type and H9 double knockout UB3A
organoids. Uh our results reveal absence
of UV3A might affect multiple cell types
not only the neurons and also uh affect
the developmental processes in human
cerebral organoids uh including cell
type compositions cell proliferations
uh organoid uh size and cortical
development.
Uh I'd be happy to take any questions in
the following poster session. Thank you
all for your time and listening.